<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rfc version="3"
     ipr="trust200902"
     category="info"
     submissionType="independent"
     docName="draft-vanta-audit-00">

  <front>
    <title>Vanta Audit Chain Specification</title>

    <author fullname="BENN" initials="B." surname="Author">
      <organization>Independent</organization>
    </author>

    <date year="2026"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document defines the Vanta audit receipt format,
        receipt chaining model, event classes, and verification rules
        for cryptographically verifiable execution tracing.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="overview">
      <name>Overview</name>
      <t>
        Vanta includes a protocol-native audit layer for important
        protocol and application events. Audit receipts are intended
        to be compact, deterministic, signed, and tamper-evident.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="events">
      <name>Audit Event Classes</name>
      <t>
        Audit receipts may be emitted for mutation application,
        duplicate handling, validation failures, retransmissions,
        and session lifecycle events.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="receipt-format">
      <name>Receipt Format</name>
      <t>
        An audit receipt contains at least a receipt identifier,
        a previous receipt hash, session and stream identifiers,
        message and operation identifiers where applicable,
        sender and receiver peer identifiers, an event type,
        a disposition code, a payload hash, a timestamp,
        and a receiver signature.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="hashing">
      <name>Payload Hashing</name>
      <t>
        Audit records MUST NOT include plaintext payload content.
        Instead, they bind to payload bytes using a cryptographic hash.
        For end-to-end encrypted payloads, the ciphertext SHOULD be
        hashed for audit binding.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="chain">
      <name>Receipt Chain Construction</name>
      <t>
        Audit receipts form an append-only hash chain. Each receipt
        commits to the previous receipt hash.
      </t>
      <sourcecode><![CDATA[
ReceiptHash_n = SHA256(CanonicalReceiptFields || PreviousReceiptHash)
]]></sourcecode>
    </section>

    <section anchor="signatures">
      <name>Receipt Signatures</name>
      <t>
        Audit receipts are signed by the receiver using its long-term
        Ed25519 identity key. This provides authenticity, attribution,
        and tamper evidence.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="verification">
      <name>Verification</name>
      <t>
        A verifier checks the receipt signature, recomputes the receipt
        hash, verifies continuity to the previous receipt hash, and
        validates the payload hash and referenced identifiers where
        available.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="continuity">
      <name>Cross-Session Continuity</name>
      <t>
        Implementations MAY support cross-session audit continuity by
        referencing the terminal receipt hash of a previous session.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="privacy">
      <name>Privacy Properties</name>
      <t>
        The audit layer intentionally stores metadata and hashes rather
        than payload contents or full application queries. This is
        intended to balance verifiability with confidentiality.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="failure">
      <name>Audit Failure Handling</name>
      <t>
        If receipt generation or verification fails under a policy that
        requires audit integrity, the implementation SHOULD emit an
        explicit protocol error and MAY terminate the session.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security-considerations">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
        Compromise of a peer's long-term signing key can invalidate
        receipt attribution for that peer. Implementations SHOULD
        protect long-term keys and receipt logs accordingly.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>Normative References</name>

      <reference anchor="RFC8032" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8032">
        <front>
          <title>Edwards-Curve Digital Signature Algorithm (EdDSA)</title>
          <author fullname="S. Josefsson" initials="S." surname="Josefsson"/>
          <author fullname="I. Liusvaara" initials="I." surname="Liusvaara"/>
          <date year="2017"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8032"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>